<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on the Nature of Reality</title>
    <description>A collection of ideas about philosophy and similar subjects
</description>
    <link>https://vityou.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://vityou.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 17:43:24 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 17:43:24 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>An Argument Against Logical Reasons</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog post encapsulates some of my thoughts on the nature of the metaphysical world, also known as what is “outside” the universe.  These ideas are by no means new, and I don’t claim to have independently come up with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to start off by assuming that everything must have a reason, and point out the illogicality that results.  I will list the premises of the argument and its conclusion, and go into more detail on each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For something to be how it is, there needs to be a reason why it is how it is, or else it would not be how it is;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We know that the universe exists;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There must be a reason that the universe exists;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There must be a reason for this reason, and so on… (this is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infinite_regress&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;infinite regress&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There can be no initial reason that every other reason stems from, since that reason would in turn need a reason;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Therefore:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is no reason the universe exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that I’m not assuming that “nothing” is the default here.  If there was nothing rather than something, then there would need to be a reason for that as well.  There just happens to be something rather than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can essentially think of the argument as a way of saying: “you can always ask why again”.  For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bob: “I bought ice cream”&lt;br /&gt;
Susan: “Why?”&lt;br /&gt;
Bob: “Because I like ice cream”&lt;br /&gt;
Susan: “Why?”&lt;br /&gt;
Bob: “Because when I eat it, my taste buds send a signal to my brain, which releases dopamine, which makes me feel good”&lt;br /&gt;
…&lt;br /&gt;
Bob: “Because the nuclei in potassium atoms are…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get the idea.  Now onto the explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-must-be-a-reason-for-everything&quot;&gt;There Must be a Reason for Everything&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what we’re assuming to be true for the sake of the argument.  If there is no reason for something to happen, it won’t happen.  Similarly, if there is a reason that something will happen, it will happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-universe-exists&quot;&gt;The Universe Exists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s not much to say about this point.  Even if our senses were completely wrong, we still know that something exists, or as René Descartes would say, “Cogito, ergo sum”, or, “I think, therefore I am”.  The part we care about is the “I am”.  As long as there is something, e.g. “I”, then that can be called the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-must-be-a-reason-that-the-universe-exists&quot;&gt;There Must be a Reason that the Universe Exists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going off of our first point, there must be a reason that the universe exists, or else it wouldn’t exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-must-be-a-reason-that-this-reason-is-valid-and-so-on&quot;&gt;There Must be a Reason that this Reason is valid, and so on…&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people think that a “reason”, includes everything about why something is how it is.  For example, the reason that I bought ice cream goes all the way up to how atoms interact with each other in my brain.  You can think of it as the reason containing all of the other reasons that lead up to itself.  Sort of like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/reason-flow.svg&quot; alt=&quot;reason flow&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;there-can-be-no-initial-reason&quot;&gt;There can be no Initial Reason&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above diagram looks nice and self-contained, but the problem arises when we try to find the innermost reason.  After all, the innermost reason is what causes all of the other reasons.  I.e. $R_{1}$ wouldn’t be true if $R_{2}$ wasn’t true.  And $R_{2}$ wouldn’t be true if $R_{3}$ wasn’t true, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason we can’t find the innermost reason is because if we did, the reason itself would need another reason to be valid.  And then that reason would need a reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;therefore-there-is-no-reason-the-universe-exists&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Therefore:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; there is no reason the universe exists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do we know?  Well for one, we know that the universe exists.  And we just showed that there is no reason that the universe exists.  This seems to be a contradiction according to our assumption, and indeed it is.  There is no reason for the universe to exist, and yet it does.  Even worse, it has a bunch of arbitrary constants and laws that have no reason to be there either.  This is why I think that the metaphysical world, or the world that the universe itself exists in, doesn’t follow the same rules of reason that we see inside the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to tell me if I’m wrong about something, or if my entire argument is complete nonsense.  I’m open to any suggestions or counterarguments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>https://vityou.github.io/an-argument-against-logical-reason.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://vityou.github.io/an-argument-against-logical-reason.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>metaphysics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
